Phillip: In this video we are going to
look at the expectations of customers.
So, what are customer expectations and why
is it important to meet or exceed them?
Maddy: Customer expectations are just
what they sound like, what the customer
expects from a service or a product.
These will be formed by a culmination of
different factors, including experience with your
organisation, the opinions they’ve heard expressed
about the product or service you offer, and the
general reputation your organisation has overall.
Phillip: Meeting and exceeding customer
expectations translates into loyal customers
and an increase in word-of-mouth sales.
Maddy: It’s important that you’re able to identify
exactly what the customer’s expectations are
and you can do this through formal channels like
surveys and feedback forms, or more informally
through natural conversations and observations.
It’s not just about a flashy website or how
good an organisation looks on paper, it is
also about the face-to-face response from staff
that makes for a good customer experience as
well as meeting and exceeding expectations.
Phillip: When you’ve established what
a customer expects, then you can then
start to plan how you’re going to
meet and exceed those expectations.
Customers don’t just purchase products and
services they are often looking for a good
feeling, solutions to problems and good aftercare.
Maddy: When a customer’s expectations
are met, it means that they have had
the experience they wanted to have when
interacting with your organization and
purchasing the product or service you offer.
This makes it more likely the customer
will probably become a return customer
themselves or may recommend you to others.
Phillip: However, meeting expectations
of the customer is not as good
as exceeding their expectations.
Although they may be happy that they got what they
wanted, by going that extra mile the experience
could be even better, which in turn would mean
that they are more likely to recommend you
and your services or products with confidence.
Maddy: When a customer’s expectations
are exceeded, you might very well
have made a customer for life!
When a customer makes the comment “my
expectations were exceeded” what they
are really saying is “I was impressed”.
Exceeding their expectations will make
them feel like they can rely on you or your
organisation to always provide them with a
quality service and offering, boosting the
likelihood of them becoming a return customer and
recommending your organization to other people.
Phillip: Unfortunately, though there may be
times when a customer may feel that their
expectations were simply not met, and this
may be for a lot of reasons, including the
possibility that the customer simply had
unrealistic expectations about what was possible.
You should, however, always take these
situations where you a customer was left
unsatisfied as learning opportunities, to
help improve your customer service, and the
product and services your organisation offers.
Maddy: Sometimes things may also go wrong
on your side, but it’s the way that you
handle things that makes all the difference.
This often doesn’t involve a big monetary
investment instead good customer service and
personal interaction with a customer can help
with expectations and improve the provision.
Phillip: What should always be remembered
is that without the customer, there would
not be an organisation as ultimately, they
are the ones that make it all possible.
By consistently meeting and exceeding the
expectations of customers you can help guarantee
a stable, loyal, and growing customer base
which can in turn then help an organisation
expand and go from strength to strength.